Register of the Czech subject collection, 1920-2010
Hoover Institution Archives
Czech Subject Collection,
1920-2010
XX752
31 manuscript boxes, 3 oversize boxes, 1 microfilm reel, 1 motion picture film reel, 1 phonorecord (14.2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Serial issues, pamphlets, election campaign literature, clandestine publications, reports, memoranda, speeches, proclamations, bulletins, leaflets, and memorabilia, relating to various aspects of twentieth-century Czechoslovak history and politics, including the Munich agreement of 1938, the Soviet invasion in 1968, the Charta 77 movement, and the end of the communist regime in 1989; and to post-1989 political, social and economic conditions, and elections, in Czechoslovakia and subsequently the independent Czech Republic. Includes photocopies of communist-era Czechoslovak government documents.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Munich four-power agreement, 1938; Czechslovakia--History; Czechslovakia--History--Intervention, 1968; Czechslovakia--Politics and government--20th century; Elections--Czechslovakia; Elections--Czech Republic; Czech Republic; Czech Republic--Politics and government; Czech Republic--Economic conditions; Czech Republic--Social conditions; Phonorecords; Moving-pictures
Collection Contents
Please see card catalog for increments that may have been received after December 1994
- SUBJECT FILE, 1918-1994. (Boxes 1-15)
  Pamphlets, booklets, bulletins, newsletters, election campaign material, newspaper issues and magazines, printed matter, pictorial charts, propaganda packets, and portfolios, photo reproductions, and miscellanea arranged chronologically and then alphabetically by subject
  - 1918-1938 (Box 1.)
    - General. "Album Representantu Vsech Oboru Verejneho Zivota Ceskoslovenskeho". Illustrated biographical dictionary of political officials, Prague, 1927. In Czech
    - Crisis, 1938 (Box 2.)
      - Czechoslovak-German, French-German, Polish newspapers issues, September 19-2l, 1938, concerning the German ultimatum for autonomy of the Sudeten Germans in Czechoslovakia and Anglo-French efforts to negotiate. Mainly in German
      - Sudeten Germans. Nemecky postup proti Slovanum a jeho Sudetsky agent. Brochure, Prag, 1938. In Czech
    - Foreign relations - Poland. Agreement between Czechoslovakia and Poland, signed on August 9, 1920, regarding settlement and compensation for state-owned property in those parts of the regions of Orava and Spis that had gone from Hungarian to Czechoslovak control on October 18, 1918, but were awarded to Poland by the Council of Ambassadors on July 20, 1920. In Czech and Polish
    - Industrial production. Reports on cement and coal production in 1922, including statistics. In German
    - Silesia. Pamphlet, 1943, issued by the Association of Cieszyn Silesians in Great Britain and relating to Cieszyn Silesia in 1919 and the recommendations of the Interallied Teschen Commission
    - Svehla, Antonin 1873-1933. Pamphlet, New York, 1953. In Czech and English
  - 1938-1945
    - Czech Army in the West. Z bombarderu za mrize by Karel Batelka. Memoirs of Czech pilot shot down over German territory. Pamphlet, 1990
    - Fucik, Julius. Fakta o Fucikovi. Dokumentace, Ostrava, 1991. Pamphlet on controversy of Fucik's political biography
    - Roosevelt, Franklin D., In Memoriam Frank Delano Roosevelt, 1882-1945. Commemorative pamphlet published by the American Institute in Prag in tribute to F.D.R., 1946
    - Western-Slav Federation. Zapadnoslovanska Federalni Unie a svaz stredoevropskych statu. Pamphlet issued by the Western Slavic Movement in Great Britain, relating to Czechoslovakia and a Central European Union, 1942. In Czech
  - 1945-1968
    - Church-state relations. Typescript relating to the situation of the Catholic Church in Czechoslovakia in 1949. In Czech
    - Education. Pamphlet, 1967, relating to state-sponsored education. In Czech
    - Emigres
      - Anti-communist opposition abroad. "Tehdy v padesatych...". Memoirs of Karel Skrabek on political movement in 1950s. Typescript. In Czech
      - Council of Free Czechoslovakia, Sudeten-German Socialdemokrats. Pamphlets issued by these and other emigre organizations, relating to post-war conditions in Czechoslovakia and Soviet take-over. In Czech, German and English, n.d. (1950s)
      - Nase Cesta. Socialisticky Casopis. Socialist periodical, Paris, 1952-1955. In Czech
    - Political trials against Lausman, Bohumil. Verdict from 1957. Typescript
  - Intervention, 1968 (Box 3.)
    - General
      - Brochures, leaflets, and posters, relating to the Soviet invasion of Czechoslovakia in August 1968. In Czech
      - Cartoons from post-invasion Czechoslovak press. Clippings
      - Press files
        - American and English. Clippings
        - Czech. Newspaper and illustrated magazine issues documenting events preceding and following invasion. In Czech
        - Emigre. Newspaper issues of Ceske Slovo, Munich, Germany
    - Chronicle of invasion. Personal letters and recollections (typescripts); Prazske jaro 68 (printed photo album), Prague, 1990; Vybor, Sept. 13 (newspaper issue covering period of August 21-31, including list of National Assembly members)
    - Communist Party of Czechoslovakia, XIIth Congress. Resolutions, brochures
    - Constitution. Draft submitted by Dubcek government. Photocopy. In English
    - Czech Bretheren Evangelical Church. Appeal to authorities for religious freedom. Typescript
    - Documentary of events. Glossy prints of newspaper covers and images of street clashes. Portfolio of published photographs (Box 4.)
    - Dubcek, Alexandr. Poster
    - Jan. Publication commemorating Jan Palach, Prague, 1990
    - New Czechoslovak government. Press release from April 8, with political biographies. Typescript
    - Rehabilitation of individuals persecuted by communists. Text of the proposed bill on judicial rehabilitation. Brochure by Svaz Protifasistickych Bojowniku. Prague, 1968
    - Religion in Communist Dominated Areas, April-May. Issues devoted to state of religious affairs in Czechoslovakia. New York
    - TRN, nos. 1-4, 1968. Satirical magazine. In Czech
  - 1968-1989 (Box 5.)
    - Acta Persecutionis: A Document from Czechoslovakia. Brochure presented to International Congress of Historical Sciences in San Francisco in 1975, listing names of persecuted individuals. Appeal to participants. Typescript
    - Komunisticka Strana Ceskoslovenska (Communist Party of Czechoslovakia)
      - Propaganda. Instructional exhibit materials
        - Anniversaries
          - Coup d'etat, 1948. 30th anniversary in 1978. Material stressing accomplishments of socialism
          - Soviet liberation of Czechoslovakia
            - 35th anniversary, 1980
            - 40th anniversary, 1985
        - Congress. Propaganda material and material refering to history of party and communist state, 1982-1989 (Box 6.)
        - Economic effectiveness. Propaganda portfolio, 1985 (Box 5.)
        - Elections of 1986. Propaganda portfolio
        - History of People's Republic. Propaganda portfolio (Box 7.)
        - Husak Gustav. Propaganda portfolio, 1974
        - May 1st. Propaganda portfolio
        - Recruiting strategies of the Communist Party. Pamphlet, 1971. In Czech
        - Revolucni Odborove Hnuti. Brochures for local activists on ideological issues, 1980-1986
        - Slovo Propagandisty a Agitatora. Monthly instructional for party activists, 1985-1986
        - Socialisticky Svaz Mladeze. Communist youth movement membership cards and statutes, 1976-1984
      - Samizdat publications
        - Obnoveni poradku by Milan Simecka, on restoration of post- 1968 communist order, 1988
        - Spion vypovida by Josef Frolik. Confessions of former secret agent, 1979. Copies of galleys
        - Zejici vysiny by Alexandr Zinovev, 1988
  - Revolution, 1989 (Box 8.)
    - General
      - Commemorative publications: brochures, booklets, catalogs, magazine issues, flyers, and miscellanea, relating to the democratization process and revolution of 1989
      - Fliers and bulletins
    - Chronicle of events. Day by day account in documents. Ked sme brali do ruk buducnost. Brochure, 1990
    - Civic Forum. Declarations, statements, proclamations, position papers, open letters, and bulletins, 1989-1990, issued by Civic Forum. In Czech and English
    - Havel, Vaclav. Speeches by and biographical information on Vaclav Havel, 1989-1990
    - Human rights and judicial freedom. Brochures on introduction of new legislation
    - Post-revolution press and magazine issues, 1990
    - World press reaction. Svet a sametova revoluce. Collection of press excerpts. Brochure. In Czech
  - 1989- (Box 9.)
    - Academy of Science. Bulletins, 1990-1991
    - Anti-communist opposition. Persons accused of anti-state activities. List based on former secret police records and published in Prague daily Noviny. Summer 1992
    - Church-state relations. "Throne of St. Peter Versus Red Star of Lenin: Vatican Relations with Poland and Czechoslovakia after 1980", 1991 and "Divergent Traditions, Converging Opposition: Nationalism and the Catholic Church in Poland and Czechoslovakia", 1990. Papers by Nina Jurewicz (typescripts); and brochure and poster on Papal visit in 1990
    - Democratization process. Government legislative documents and new decrees, 1990-1991
    - Hornak, Viliam, Ceskoslovensko mezi prestavbou a revoluci (Politicky denik 1987-1991). Political diary. Prague, 1991. Brochure
    - Moravia and Silesia. Fliers and brochures illustrating local developments in the region, 1990-1993
    - Political analysis
      - General
      - Association for Independent Social Analysis, Bulletins, 1990. Analysis of all aspects of social transformation
      - Budovani statu. Prehledy ceskoslovenske politiky. Review of political developments in Czech and Slovak Republics 1992-1994
    - Political parties (Box 10.)
      - General
        - General
        - Bulletins
        - Material related to various aspects of political life in Moravia and Silesia. Fliers, bulletins, posters
      - Demokraticka Strana Czeskoslovenska, Hlas Demokracie. Official party organ, newspaper issues, 1990-1991
      - Komunisticeska Strana Ceskoslovenska, Mosty. Official party weekly. Newspaper issues, 1990-1991
      - Leva Alternativa, Polarita. Official party publication. Newspaper issues, 1990-1991
      - Prazska Antikomunisticeska Inicjativa, Rude Kravo. Official party publication on history of repression under communist regime. Newspaper issues, 1992. Includes lists of secret police agents and collaborators (Box 11.)
      - Radikalna Repubblikanska Strana, Radikalni Republikanin. Official party publication. Newspaper issues, 1991
      - Republikanska Unie, Republikanske Listy. Official party publication. Newspaper issues, 1990-1991
      - Republikanska Strana Czeskoslovenska, Republika. Official party publication. Newspaper issues, 1990
    - Programs for elections. Flyers, leaflets, brochures, booklets, newspaper issues, posters, and insignia issued by various political parties (Box 12.)
      - 1990 June.
        - General
          - General
          - Candidates and parties participating. Lists
        - Ceskoslovenska Strana Socialisticka
        - Liberalna Demokraticka Strana
        - Komunisticka Strana Ceskoslovenska
        - Krestansko Demokraticka Strana
        - Obcanske Forum (Box 13.)
      - 1992 June
        - General
          - Candidates. Lists and programs
          - Plzen region. Miscellany
          - Polish minority candidates. Miscellany
        - Agrarian parties
        - Ceskoslovenska Socialni Demokracie (Box 14.)
        - Levy Blok
        - Liberalne Socialni Unie
        - Mladi Socialni Demokrate
        - Obcanska Demokraticka Aliance
        - Obcanska Demokraticka Strana (Box 15.)
        - Obcanske Hnuti
    - Privatization. Fliers promoting various investment funds and newspaper issues, 1992-1993
    - State security officers fired after inestigation. List compiled in February 1993. Copy of typescript
- PERIODICALS, 1990-1994. (Box 16)
  Periodical issues relating mostly to the early period of shaping of new democracy, following the 1989 revolution
  - General (Box 16.)
    - General
    - Catholic and other religious denominations publications
    - Moravian and Silesian publications
  - Aktuality, Tvorba, Dialog, Prague, 1990
  - Jedenadvacet, Prague, 1990
  - Katolicke Noviny, Prague, 1989
  - Katolicky Tydenik, Prague, 1990
  - Kuryr, Plzen, 1990
  - Narodni Osvobozeni, Prague, 1991
  - Pegas, Ostrava, 1990
  - Plznenske Noviny, Plzen, 1991
  - Zvlastni Vydani, Brno, 1990-1991
- MEMORABILIA, 1989-1994. (Box 17)
  Election party pins and stickers, tote bags, communist organizations medals, communist insignia, woven fabric with images of communist leaders
  - Election party pins and stickers, tote bags, communist organizations medals, communist insignia, woven fabric with images of communist leaders (Box 17.)
- OVERSIZE MATERIAL. (Box 18)
  Nine drawings by school children depicting street scenes from 1989
  - Nine drawings by school children, depicting street scenes from 1989 events (Box 18.)
- AUDIO-VISUAL MATERIAL. (Microfilm cabinet, Film shelf)
  One microfilm reel of documents on the Soviet invasion of Czechoslovakia and one motion picture (l6mm) depicting the Soviet entrance into Prague in August 1968
  - One microfilm reel of documents on the Soviet invasion of Czechoslovakia in August 1968 (Oversize Microfilm cabinet)
  - One phonorecord, "Svaty Otec Jan Pavel II u nas," 1990 (Oversize Record cabinet, Record cabinet)
    A recording released on occassion of Pope John Paul II trip's to Czechoslovakia
  - One motion picture (l6mm) depicting the Soviet entrance into Prague, with a sound track in French, entitled "Entrie des Russes ` Prague, 2l August 1968" (Shelf Film shelf)